The first time I stood in the operating room
اول مرة وقفت في غرفة العمليات
and watched a real surgery,
وشاهدت عملية جراحية حقيقية
I had no idea what to expect.
لم تكن لدي أدنى فكرة عن ماذا سيحصل
I was a college student in engineering.
كنت طالب في كلية الهندسة
I thought it was going to be like on TV.
كنت اتوقع انها ستكون مماثلة لما في التلفاز
Ominous music playing in the background,
موسيقى حزينة تشتغل في الخلفية
beads of sweat pouring down the surgeon's face.
قطرات من العرق تنزل من وجه الجراح
But it wasn't like that at all.
لكن لم يكن الأمر هكذا ابداً
There was music playing on this day,
كانت هناك موسيقى ذلك اليوم
I think it was Madonna's greatest hits. (Laughter)
اعتقد انها من البوم لمادونا
And there was plenty of conversation,
وكان هناك العديد من المحادثات
not just about the patient's heart rate,
ليس مجرد عن نبضات قلب المريض
but about sports and weekend plans.
لكن عن الرياضة و مخططات العطلة
And since then, the more surgeries I watched,
ومنذ ذلك الحين , كلما رأيت المزيد من العمليات الجراحية
the more I realized this is how it is.
كلما ادركت ان هذه كيفية اجرائها
In some weird way, it's just another day at the office.
بطريقة او بأخرى , إنها يوم آخر في المكتب
But every so often
لكن في احيان كثيرة
the music gets turned down,
يتم خفض صوت الموسيقى
everyone stops talking,
ويتوقف الجميع عن الحديث
and stares at exactly the same thing.
ويتم التركيز على نفس الشيء
And that's when you know that something absolutely critical
وهذا عندما تعرف , أن هناك شيء حرج جداً
and dangerous is happening.
الخطر يحدث
The first time I saw that
في أول مرة أرى هذا
I was watching a type of surgery
كن أرى نوعا ًمن العمليات
called laparoscopic surgery
يعرف بالجراحة بالمنظار
And for those of you who are unfamiliar,
و لمن من هم ليسوا على دراية
laparoscopic surgery, instead of the large
الجراحة بالمنظار , عوضاً عن شق
open incision you might be used to with surgery,
فتحة كبيرة للعملية
a laparoscopic surgery is where the surgeon creates
الجراحة بالمنظار , هي عندما يفتح الجراح
these three or more small incisions in the patient.
ثلاث شقوق صغيرة او أكثر في المريض
And then inserts these long, thin instruments
ثم يتم إدخال أدوات طويلة ونحيفة
and a camera,
مع كاميرا
and actually does the procedure inside the patient.
وفي الحقيقة تجرى العلمية داخل المريض
This is great because there's much less risk of infection,
هذا شيء متميز , لأنه يتسبب في إنقاص نسبة حدوث تلوث
much less pain, shorter recovery time.
واقل ألماً بالإضافة إلى سرعة الشفاء
But there is a trade-off,
لكن هناك سلبية
because these incisions are created
لأن الفتحات تفتح عبر
with a long, pointed device
أداة ثقب طويلة
called a trocar.
تسمى ( التروكار )
And the way the surgeon uses this device
والطريقة التي يستخدم فيها الجراح هذه الأداة
is that he takes it
انه يأخذها
and he presses it into the abdomen
ويضغط بها بإتجاه البطن
until it punctures through.
حتى تثقب البطن
And now the reason why everyone in the operating room
والسببب أن كل من في غرفة العمليات
was staring at that device on that day
يحدقون في هذا الجهاز في ذلك اليوم
was because he had to be absolutely careful
لأن يجب ان يكون في غاية الحذر
not to plunge it through
ان لا يثقب بعمق
and puncture it into the organs and blood vessels below.
فيثقب الأعضاء والأوعية الدموية في الأسفل
But this problem should seem pretty familiar to all of you
لكن المشكلة يجب ان تكون معروفة لديكم
because I'm pretty sure you've seen it somewhere else.
لأني متأكد أنها مرت عليك من قبل
(Laughter)
( ضحك )
Remember this?
تتذكرون ذلك ؟
(Applause)
( تصفيق )
You knew that at any second
تعرفون أنه في أي لحظة
that straw was going to plunge through,
أن اقصبة الشرب ستندفع للخارج
and you didn't know if it was going to go out the other side
لكن لا تعرف , هل ستثقب الجهة الأخرى
and straight into your hand,
و تتجه مباشرة نحو يدك
or if you were going to get juice everywhere,
أم سيتسبب في تطاير العصير في كل مكان
but you were terrified. Right?
لكنك في حالة ذعر، صحيح ؟
Every single time you did this,
في كلة لحظة تفعل هذا ،
you experienced the same fundamental physics
انت تختبر نفس العملية الفيزيائية
that I was watching in the operating room that day.
عنما كنت أشاهد العملية الجراحية ذلك اليوم
And it turns out it really is a problem.
وأتضح أنها فعلاً مشكلة
In 2003, the FDA actually came out and said
في 2003 ,ادارة الاغذية والعقاقير صرحوا بأن
that trocar incisions might be the most dangerous step
الثقب عبر التروكار ربما تكون أكثر الخطوات خطورة
in minimally invasive surgery.
على الأقل في العمليات الجراحية
Again in 2009, we see a paper that says
مرة أخرى في 2009 هناك مقال يُفيد
that trocars account for over half
بأن التروكار يشكل اكثر من نصف
of all major complications in laparoscopic surgery.
التعقيدات الرئيسية في الجراحة بالمنظار
And, oh by the way,
وعلى فكرة
this hasn't changed for 25 years.
هذا لم يتغير منذ 25 سنة
So when I got to graduate school,
وبالتالي عندما تخرجت من الجامعة ,
this is what I wanted to work on.
هذا ما أردت ان اعمل عليه
I was trying to explain to a friend of mine
كنت أحاول أن اشرح لأحد اصدقائي
what exactly I was spending my time doing,
ماذا كنت اقضي وقتي فاعلاً
and I said,
و قلت ,
"It's like when you're drilling through a wall
" إنه مثل عندما تريد أن تثقب الحائط ,
to hang something in your apartment.
لتعليق شيء في شقتك
There's that moment when the drill first punctures through the wall
هناك تلك اللحظة عندما يخرج الدريل بعد ثقب الحائط
and there's this plunge. Right?
و هناك يحدث الإندفاع , صحيح ؟
And he looked at me and he said,
ثم نظر إلي و قال ,
And I said, "Excuse me?" (Laughter)
ثم قلت , إسمح لي ؟ (ضحك )
And then I looked it up and they do drill into people's brains.
ثم بحثت و علمت أنهم فعلاً يثقبون أدمغة الناس
A lot of neurosurgical procedures
الكثير من عمليات جراحة الأعصاب
actually start with a drill incision through the skull.
فعلاَ , يبدأون بعمل ثقب في الجمجمة
And if the surgeon isn't careful,
وإذا لم يكن الجراح حذر ,
he can plunge directly into the brain.
يمكنه أن يندفع مباشرة داخل الدماغ
So this is the moment when I started thinking,
وبالتالي تلك اللحظة عندما بدأت أفكر ,
okay, cranial drilling, laparoscopic surgery,
حسناً , ثقب الجمجمة , عمليات المنظار
why not other areas of medicine?
لمذا لا تتواجد في غيرها من المجالات الطبية
Because think about it, when was the last time you went to the doctor
قكر في الأمر , متى آخر مرة ذهبت للدكتور ؟
and you didn't get stuck with something? Right?
و لم تتعثر في شيء ؟صحيح؟
So the truth is
إذاً الحقيقة هي
in medicine puncture is everywhere.
في الطب كل شيء يتعلق بالثقب
And here are just a couple of the procedures that I've found
وهناك فقط نوعين من العمليات التي عرفت
that involve some tissue puncture step.
أن الثقب إحدى خطواتها
And if we take just three of them —
فإذا اخذنا ثلاثة منهم فقط
laparoscopic surgery, epidurals, and cranial drilling —
عملية المنظار , التهاب الجافية و ثقب الجمجمة
these procedures account for over 30,000 complications
هذه العمليات تشكل أكثر من 30,000 عملية معقدة
every year in this country alone.
سنوياً في هذه الدولة لوحدها
I call that a problem worth solving.
اعتبر هذه مشكلة تستحق الحل
So let's take a look at some of the devices
إذا لنأخذ نظرة على بعض الأدوات
that are used in these types of procedures.
هذة تستخدم في هذا النوع من العمليات
I mentioned epidurals. This is an epidural needle.
ذكر التهاب الجافية , هذه الإبرة المستخدمة
It's used to puncture through the ligaments in the spine
إنها تستخدم من خلال الثقب في اربطة العمود الفقري
and deliver anesthesia during childbirth.
وتستخدم في التخدير في عمليات الولادة
Here's a set of bone marrow biopsy tools.
وهنا مجموعة من الأدوات التي نستخدمها لتحليل النخاع العظمي
These are actually used to burrow into the bone
هذه في الحقيقة تستعمل في الحفر داخل العظم
and collect bone marrow or sample bone lesions.
لتجمع أجزاء من النخاع العظمي او عينات من إصابات العظم
Here's a bayonette from the Civil War.
وهنا حربة من الحرب العالمية
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
If I had told you it was a medical puncture device
إذا قلت لكم أنها اداة ثقب طبية
you probably would have believed me.
ربما ستصدقونني .
Because what's the difference?
والسبب , أين الأختلاف ؟
So, the more I did this research
إذاً , كلما بحثت أكثر
the more I thought there has to be
كلما تأكدت أنه يجب أن يكون هناك
a better way to do this.
طريقة أفضل لفعل هذا ,
And for me the key to this problem
وبالنسبة لي مفتاح المشكلة
is that all these different puncture devices
أن جميع أدوات الثقب
share a common set of fundamental physics.
تتشارك في أحد المبادئ الأساسية في الفيزياء
So what are those physics?
إذا ما هو هذا المبدئ ؟
Let's go back to drilling through a wall.
فلنرجع قليلاً للثقب داخل الحائط
So you're applying a force on a drill towards the wall.
إذا أنت بإستخدام الدريل , تنشئ قوة موجهه بإتجاه الجدار
And Newton says the wall is going to apply force back,
وقانون نيوتن ينص على أن الجدار سيبذل قوة في الإتجاه المعاكس
equal and opposite.
مساويه و معاكسة
So, as you drill through the wall,
إذاً . أثناء عملية الثقب داخل الحائط
those forces balance.
جميع القوى تكون متساوية
But then there's that moment
لكن هناك تلك اللحظة
when the drill first punctures through the other side of the wall,
عدما يخرج الدريل لأول مرة من الجهة الأخرى للحائط
and right at that moment the wall can't push back anymore.
وفي تلك اللحظة تحديداً ,الحائط لا يستيطع بذل القوة المعاكسة بعد الآن
But your brain hasn't reacted to that change in force.
لكن عقلك لم يستوعب بعد التغيير في مقدار القوة
So for that millisecond,
إذا في هذا الجزء من الثانية,
or however long it takes you to react, you're still pushing,
مع ذا مهما طال بك الوقت لتستجيب , انت مازلت تدفع
and that unbalanced force causes an acceleration,
وهذا التغيير في مقدار القوى يتسبب في حدوث تسارع
and that is the plunge.
وهذا هو الإندفاع المفاجئ
But what if right at the moment of puncture
لكن ماذا إذا استطعنا في لحظة الإندفاع المفاجئ
you could pull that tip back,
أن نسحب المثقاب مرة أخرى
actually oppose the forward acceleration?
في الحقيقة عبارة تسارع في الإتجاه المعاكس
That's what I set out to do.
هذا ما عزمت على فعله
So imagine you have a device
إذاً تخيل أنك تملك أداة
and it's got some kind of sharp tip to cut through tissue.
وتمتلك طرفاً حاداً لتجري ثقباً في منديل
What's the simplest way you could pull that tip back?
ما هي أسهل طريقة لإرجاع الطرف الحاد مرة أخرى ؟
I chose a spring.
انا اخترت النابض
So when you extend that spring, you extend that tip out
إذا عندما يتمدد النابض يكون الرأس في الخارج
so it's ready to puncture tissue,
و يصبح جاهزاً لثقب الأنسجة
the spring wants to pull the tip back.
والنابض يصر على سحب الرأس الحاد للداخل
How do you keep the tip in place
إذا كيف نبقي الرأس الحاد ثابتاً
until the moment of puncture?
حتى تحين لحظة الثقب ؟
I used this mechanism.
أنا استعملت التقنية التالية
When the tip of the device is pressed against tissue,
إذا كان الرأس الحاد يضغط باتجاه الأنسجة
the mechanism expands outwards and wedges in place against the wall.
الأداة تمتد للخارج والزوايا تلتصق بالحائط
And the friction that's generated
و الاحتكاك الناتج
locks it in place and prevents the spring from retracting the tip.
يبقى في مكانه ثابتاَ مما يمنع النابض من الرجوع للخلف
But right at the moment of puncture,
و لكن حين تحين لحظة الثقب
the tissue can't push back on the tip anymore.
الأنسجة لا تستطيع مقاومة الرأس الحاد بعد الآن
So the mechanism unlocks and the spring retracts the tip.
فيتم الغاء التأمين و يرجع الرأس الحاد عبر النابض
Let me show you that happening in slow motion.
اسمحوا لي أن اعرض لك ما حدث بالحركة البطيئة
This is about 2,000 frames a second,
هذا عبارة عن 20,000 اطار في الثانية
and I'd like you to notice the tip
واود منكم ان تلاحظوا الرأس الحاد
that's right there on the bottom, about to puncture through tissue.
المتواجد هناك في الأسفل على وشك خرق الانسجة
And you'll see that right at the moment of puncture,
وسوف تشاهد ذالك ان في اللحظة المحددة للثقب
right there, the mechanism unlocks and retracts that tip back.
في تلك اللحظة , التقنية تعمل وتقوم بسحب الرأس مرة اخرى
I want to show it to you again, a little closer up.
اريد ان اريكم ذلك مرة اخرى , اقرب قليلاً
You're going to see the sharp bladed tip,
سوف تشاهد الرأس الحاد الأبيض
and right when it punctures that rubber membrane
وحين تقوم بثقب ذلك الغشاء المطاطي
it's going to disappear into this white blunt sheath.
سوف تقوم بالإختفاء بداخل ذلك الأنبوب الأبيض
Right there.
هناك
That happens within four 100ths of a second after puncture.
هذا يحدث بعد الثقب في غضون 100 جزء من الثانية
And because this device is designed to address the physics of puncture
ولأن الأداة تم تصميمها لمعالجة فيزيائية الثقب
and not the specifics of cranial drilling
وليس مخصصة لثقب الجمجمة
or laparoscopic surgery, or another procedure,
او الجراحة بالمنظار , او اي عملية جراحية
it's applicable across these different medical disciplines
فإنها قابلة للتطبيق على مختلف العمليات الجراحية
and across different length scales.
وعلى مختلف القياسات
But it didn't always look like this.
ولكن لا تبدو هكذا دائماً
This was my first prototype.
هذا هو النموذج الأولي
Yes, those are popsicle sticks,
هذه هي عصيان للسحب
and there's a rubber band at the top.
وهناك شريط مطاطي في الأعلى
It took about 30 minutes to do this, but it worked.
اسغرقت حوالي 30 دقيقة في فعل هذا , وعمل بنجاح
And it proved to me that my idea worked
وأثبت لي ان فكرتي عملت
and it justified the next couple years of work on this project.
وهذا سوغ لي العمل في هذا المشروع لسنتين متتاليتين
I worked on this because
عملت على هذا لأن
this problem really fascinated me.
المشكلة شدتني بشدة ,
It kept me up at night.
ابقتني مستيقظاً في الليل
But I think it should fascinate you too,
لكن اتوقع انها يجب ان تشدك ايضاً
because I said puncture is everywhere.
لأنني كما قلت ان عمليات الثقب في كل مكان
That means at some point it's going to be your problem too.
مما يعني انها في احد المراحل ستكون مشكلتك ايضاً
That first day in the operating room
ذاك اليوم في غرفة العمليات
I never expected to find myself on the other end of a trocar.
لم اكن اتوقع ان اجد نفسي في الجهة الاخرى ممسكا بالثاقب
But last year, I got appendicitis when I was visiting Greece.
لكن في السنة الأخيرة , أصبت بالزائدة الدودية أثناء زيارتي لليونان
So I was in the hospital in Athens,
لذكا كنت في مشفى في أثينا
and the surgeon was telling me
والجراح كان يخبرني
he was going to perform a laparoscopic surgery.
هو سيقوم بأداء عملية جراحية بالمنظار
He was going to remove my appendix through these tiny incisions,
و سيقوم بإزالة الزائدة الدودية عبر تلك الفتحات الصغيرة
and he was talking about what I could expect for the recovery,
وكان يتحدث عن الاعراض اللتي يجب ان اتوقعها لفترة النقاهة
and what was going to happen.
وماذا سيحدث ,
He said, "Do you have any questions?" And I said, "Just one, doc.
قال لي : "هل تملك اي سؤال"؟ رددت : سؤال واحد دكتور.
What kind of trocar do you use?"
ما نوع التروكار الذي ستسخدمه ؟
So my favorite quote about laparoscopic surgery
إذا افضل عبارة سمعتها عن الجراحة بالمنظار
comes from a Doctor H. C. Jacobaeus:
اتت من الدكتور جابكايس
"It is puncture itself that causes risk."
" عملية الثقب بحد ذاتها هي مصدر للخطر "
That's my favorite quote because H.C. Jacobaeus
هذه افضل عبارة لأن الدكتور جابكايس
was the first person to ever perform laparoscopic surgery on humans,
كان اول شخص اجرى الجراحة بالمنظار على الإنسان
and he wrote that in 1912.
وكتب ذلك في عام 1912
This is a problem that's been injuring and even killing people for over 100 years.
هذه مشكلة تتسبب بإصابة و قتل البشر لمدة تزيد عن مئة عام
So it's easy to think that for every major problem out there
إذا من السهل التفكير بأن كل مشكلة كبيرة تحيط بنا
there's some team of experts working around the clock to solve it.
هناك مجموعة من الخبراء كرسوا اوقاتهم لحلها
The truth is that's not always the case.
الحقيقة هذا ليس هو الحال دائماً
We have to be better at finding those problems
يجب ان نتحسن في ايجاد تلك المشاكل
and finding ways to solve them.
و إيجاد الطرق لحلها
So if you come across a problem that grabs you,
إذاً, اذا مررت بمشكلة تقلقك
let it keep you up at night.
دعها تبقيك مستيقظاً في الليل
Allow yourself to be fascinated,
اسمح لنفسك ان تكون مولعاً بحلها
because there are so many lives to save.
لأن هناك العديد من الأرواح تحتاج للإنقاذ
(Applause)
( تصفيق )